<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Justin Kropp</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2024-02-08T11:14:12-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Justin Kropp</name>
   <email>justinkropp@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>False Idols</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/false-idols"/>
   <updated>2024-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/false-idols</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every profession has its version of celebrity practitioner. Some professions have many, while others seem to just have a small handful that make the rounds for years in publications, conferences, panels, etc. In graphic design, Stefan Sagmeister was a the closest thing we had to a rock star, and he remained the exalted one for years. In standards-based web design it was Jeffrey Zeldman. Flash? Joshua Davis. In digital product design there seem to be countless that tread at the top, in part due to the many disciplines that are squished together and encapsulated in the term “product design”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our profession – design (web, product, etc) – has its idols. Folks we look up to for their design acumen and body of work, whether that work is applied or theoretical. It’s only natural – human nature even – to place these practitioners we admire up on a pedestal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seldom do we get to meet them and even more seldom do we get to work alongside them. We only know the image that we’ve abstracted from what we’ve seen at conference talks, interviews online, or perhaps in podcasts they host or have been guests on. The constructed image is illusory at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is unwise to seek personal acquaintance with people whom one has regarded with high esteem, as they often fail to fulfill one’s expectations, resulting in disappointment.
— ancient proverb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One hundred percent this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had the opportunity to work alongside someone whose work and writing I had admired for some time. Probably the better part of a decade. I’d read his book, watched his conference talks, and followed his growing body of work. He had an eloquent way of speaking about our craft as designers and could break down complex ideas into easy to digest chunks with what seemed like ease. He seemed like an affable dude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got to know him, I realized that those things I admired about him were more about the work and the approach to the work, and had nothing to do with the person. The person was an entirely different… experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say I was disappointed would be an understatement. But this disappointment is on me. I made the mistake of not only putting his work on a pedestal, I put him there too. And that’s not fair. We are never our work, I hope, and never should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your profession is not your personality. Reducing yourself to any single characteristic, whether it be your title or your job performance, is a deeply damaging act.
— Arthur C. Brooks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Levity</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/levity"/>
   <updated>2024-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/levity</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I heard a comedian telling a story about friend who was describing what their day job was like, and this person described it as: &lt;em&gt;doing serious work for serious people seriously.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I could think of at the time was how uninspired that work must be. How exhausting it must be to slog through that kind of environment day after day.  After some reflection I realized that my own experience has taught me that this &lt;em&gt;state of being in the workplace&lt;/em&gt; is all too common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it’s not directly analogous to the above, but I’ve certainly worked on teams and under senior leadership that took their work all too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a correlation between taking your work too seriously and a level of self importance that borders on delusions of grandeur. This parallel is especially rampant in Silicon Valley, where “make a dent in the universe” has been the mantra &lt;em&gt;de jure&lt;/em&gt; since the late ‘80s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s the position you want to operate from, fine, but understand the reality of that perspective and the unintended consequences it can have for those working under its weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can have a deleterious effect to the atmosphere in which the work is being done and the stakes of that work become artificially elevated. Over time this will erode morale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A constant expression of importance can impede the ability to make sound product decisions that are grounded in reality (also something in short supply throughout the Bay Area).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A work culture like this will ultimately squeeze wit from the product and push levity out of the equation altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lack of levity will, at best, lead to burnout and, at worst, birth resentment. Both will degrade the quality of the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lead-with-levity&quot;&gt;Lead with levity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levity can be used as a guideline for how we approach our own work as well as how we ask other to approach theirs. It can provide the margin we need to take more risks and push the perimeter out a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levity frees us up to drop the pretension of product or service the company has socialized and just focus on doing good work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can look at the problems through a different shade lens and  with some wit or humor we can inject some emotion back into the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can drop our shoulders and take safe harbor in knowing that what we’re actually building isn’t urgent or life changing, and that’s okay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often do our best work when we execute small things really well. Those small things are always part of bigger things, and those bigger things will benefit from those small things being done with the utmost care, craft, and with a bit of levity behind it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing levity will benefit your entire organization.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>JOMO</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/jomo"/>
   <updated>2024-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/jomo</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like many of us I tend to pass some of my downtime or in-between time by browsing social media or mindlessly ingesting a palette of headlines from &lt;em&gt;insert news org here&lt;/em&gt;. Last year I realized that my social media habits were simply a surrogate for a feeling of connectedness to the world and what was going on in the small circles of interest I followed. The news simply served as a way for me to navigate making sense of what was going on in the world at large. Both habits — social media and the news — were a kind of participatory activity predicated on FOMO. If a friend asked “did you hear about so and so” I could respond — confidently — yes, and then we could riff. Or if, while thumbing down my Instagram feed, I got sucked into some video from Huberman or Attia I would feel like it was time well spent because I had gained some new knowledge about morning sunlight or some bio-marker that I really need to get checked for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If not kept in check, these behaviors move stealthily from intentional to aimless and eat up more and more of our time. Anything for that quick hit of dopamine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Months ago I made the decision to get off all social media and stop seeking out knowing what’s going on in the world. I needed to free up some brain space as well as some time. I’ve since noticed a striking difference in how calm my mind feels and how much space I now have to dedicate to things that are actually important to me. I’ve realized that none of what I was seeking through those channels was neither important nor contributing to a better me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, instead of FOMO, I take pride JOMO: joy of missing out. When a friend now asks “did you hear about &lt;em&gt;some shit&lt;/em&gt;”, I love saying: “nope”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try it for a day. Then a couple days. Once you hit a week, kudos. Now just keep that going. You’re not missing out on anything. I promise.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
